[SPEAKER_02]: So, how is it going now?
[SPEAKER_02]: Did you start...?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, actually... Actually, first thing I want to know is, actually, many monks, they ask me, the... what's the problem, about their understanding of dependent origination.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I asked for Venerable Panyu, he said, it's not necessary for me to know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: He thought that maybe...
[SPEAKER_00]: I get confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually, simply, I don't understand what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, because I studied only the teaching of, you know, the timeless creation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think in Srilanka, most monks, they don't, eh... they don't understand that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They think, like, it's a process.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's like two lines or three lines, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: What they're talking about, I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's very difficult for me to explain what Venerable Nyanavilla taught.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you explain to them?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I don't think... You have to start with a premise that they already have a different view.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't want to say they have a wrong view, but yeah, from Nyanavilla's point of view, that's a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wrong view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they approach Patiṭṭhā Upādā as an explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: I remember Bhikkhu Bodhi, he was very, very much sharing the traditional view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, and he would write, write about it and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he would say that,
[SPEAKER_02]: No, this is not... not the core of the dhamma as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: This is more like an encompassing explanation of the entire teaching and the purpose of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in a way, when you look at it, well, okay, that... like, it's not wrong, because what... any aspect of the dhamma contains the entire dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can say, in relation to anything, that it encompasses the entire dhamma, because it can be enough for somebody to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: However, the Buddha himself said, well, Sariputta said, dhamma is paticca-sampādha, paticca-sampādha is dhamma, dhamma-sīla, dhamma-sīla, which means, oh, no, it's actually quite... and then the Buddha also referred to paticca-sampādha as the reason.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not knowing that is why people remain bound to saṃsara.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's actually not an explanation of some ideal, an overview.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a very direct insight.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the fact is that
[SPEAKER_02]: Every patiṣṭha upādāna formulation in the suttas starts first by saying, with arising... with this, this is, or with the arising of this, this arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already akālika.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, with the presence of this, this is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't say, as Nibiru pointed out, if you adopt the three-life interpretation, it will be with this arising of this, and then ceasing, then this arises, then it ceases, then something else arises, then it ceases, then something else...
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It says with the arising of this, this is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the determination, the reason, the cause, is present simultaneously with that which is being determined.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he would... the Buddha would say himself, with the arising of what?
[SPEAKER_02]: This is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he would formulate paticca upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Bhikkhu Bodhi was aware of that, because, you know, his pāli is very good.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he would... he would refuse to give up his view of three-life interpretation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then he would dismiss this opening statement with this, this is, and say, ah, this is just an abstract principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, even... even an abstract principle is still a principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whether it's an abstract or not, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: But by saying abstract, you dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact is, it's a principle within which the whole dhamma is contained.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you dismiss that, and then your interpretation of that paticcaṁ pada goes against the principle, means that's a contradiction, and that's why it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he always, always just, ah, this is just an abstract principle, and then puts it aside by labeling it such, and then goes on
[SPEAKER_02]: into expounding how the feeling connection and this...
[SPEAKER_02]: I even forgot what the traditional interpretation was.
[SPEAKER_02]: Long time, Reddit.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you had other people said, well, it doesn't pertain...
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that was K. Yananda there, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was saying, doesn't pertain to three life, it pertains to one life.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, he took it as an explanation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, as a kind of explaining what's happening.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, if you're explaining what's happening, then it loses the aspect of opanaiko, leading on, that the Buddha talked about.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if I provide you an explanation, you can say, oh, yes, or we can say, oh, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It stops there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it just remains at the level of intellect and the view.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if the Buddha describes something,
[SPEAKER_02]: That in order for you to understand, it leads you on to more understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: That means, ah, that has the nature of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to bear that in mind when you try to explain to somebody who already has a different view.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are very little chances of them understanding it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because... it is possible for them to understand, but it has to come from them.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, they first have to see that they're wrong,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you have to start looking out for what is less wrong, in terms of their current view.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, they might be recipient to hear it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're just trying to convince somebody otherwise, it's useless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Varapanyo, he said, actually, if we try to understand the teaching of Venerable Ñānavīr, timeless relation, and then the past and the future, both are not important, he said.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a traditional interpretation program that past and the future... Oh, I see what you mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, whether it's your past, whether it's your future, it's present as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: Past is present, future is present, and the present is present, which is the nature of humanism.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's immediacy and reflection.
[SPEAKER_02]: Two modes of existence, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you think about your past, you think it in your present.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you think about your present, you think it in your present.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you think about your future, you think in the present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you abandon that present, in terms of you fully understand it, then neither your past, nor future, nor that which is right in front of you, can pertain to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, yeah, absolutely, it's not important anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if the past would be important for the practice of the dhamma, well, you couldn't practice the dhamma, because you can't change what has happened.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the future would be important in terms of how you just have to wait and it will happen by itself, well, then, again, you can never know that directly for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just take it on faith and believe, which is actually what most of religions rely on.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just this belief that eventually it will all work out fine for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, like, well, okay, good luck then.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what makes you think so?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, in the cases of people who had horrible past, like Angulimala or other, you know, if they can overturn that and escape that sort of past...
[SPEAKER_02]: But he couldn't, certainly, he couldn't undo what he'd done.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he'd done some serious things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you realize, ah, it's in the present, which is why I would have said it's here and now, visible here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to wait for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you don't have to remember it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's here and now.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, in the same sense, he called it opanaika and called it timeless, not pertaining to time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, that's exactly how it doesn't pertain.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it was pertaining to time, it would pertain to past.
[SPEAKER_02]: It would require future.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's timeless, which means, ah... Because, if... if past is present, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: One thing is present, like... how to put it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_02]: Past is in present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's a timeless relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present is in the present.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's another timeless relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: Future is, as future, in the present.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you look at it from the point of view of present, even if it's present what you're looking at, that's a timeless relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: So if you understand that, then whatever particularly was that past you were thinking of, or whatever particular thoughts were pertaining for the future, that's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you abandoned present, which means you abandoned past, future and present that were in the present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So nothing is left out.
[SPEAKER_02]: And in terms of not having to understand paticca upādāna, well, that's true in a sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't have to
[SPEAKER_02]: Understand all of the individual factors, the way the Buddha laid them down, because they're quite subtle themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you need to understand this timeless principle, which is, which is why the Buddha called atiṣṇupāda dhamma dhamma patiṣṇupāda.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, was it... One who sees the... One who sees the Buddha, sees the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: One who sees the dhamma, sees the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, that's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, Sariputra said, in terms of dhamma and paticampadaya, or Buddha or paticampadaya.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mithushu said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Either way, you don't have to understand all the specific factors of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have to understand that principle that Bhikkhu Bodhi dismisses as abstract.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you understand that all of these things are implied.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the fact that the Buddha
[SPEAKER_02]: Quite often, eh... described the Tīṣṇhapāda differently.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes it would... it would have 12 factors, sometimes it would have 15 factors, sometimes it would stop at nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, viññāṇa, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would omit the whole viññāṇa, sankhāra, and then sankhāra, avijjā.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would just... he just wouldn't talk about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you realize, oh, it's an exemplification of a... of a principle that can be laid out in... in different ways.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's still the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you dismiss the principle, you get bogged down in, well, in the detail, which becomes, basically, you have to explain it, you have to find the connections, and it becomes linear, psychological, traditional, commentarial.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you keep the principle in mind, as something that has been understood, then you might even not think in terms of
[SPEAKER_02]: The way the Buddha laid it down, the whole Patitsangpa, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You understood the principle, and freed you from ignorance, and it's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, all of those individual factors, if you can refer to them as such, it's not 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
[SPEAKER_02]: They're all present simultaneously, just on different layers.
[SPEAKER_02]: Present on different layers within the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it is all simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't mean that, again, you can approach it, you can think in terms of these twelve factors arising at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends how you look at it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The principle arises at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, if you take it further, you can start defining the same principle further and further and further.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how those factors were defined.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not... it's not more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And certainly, it's not about, like, drawing a linear connection between the factors and trying to present a chart that will really encompass it all.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just... that's kind of... well, that is definitely pointless and won't... won't bring any... well, any timeless understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think, in the end, I will also mention in one of the letters, when somebody asking, well, like,
[SPEAKER_02]: This is the first time that they heard that somebody defines pāṇḍa like that, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were not disagreeing with him, but they were just curious.
[SPEAKER_02]: How's that?
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well, like, you know, you might have another sort of pāṇḍa who wouldn't necessarily think in those terms.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if he didn't approach it through that way, in terms of understanding, he won't be able to recognize
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what he will recognize, what he will know, is the principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: With this, this is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's, that's, that principle is contained in, in that, like, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: The representative insight of a sotāpanna, which is whatever has the nature of arising, for that reason, has the nature of ceasing, because it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, permanence is implied.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how the being gets undone.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, again, it's not that, you know, for sotāpanna, for anārahaṃ, those twelve factors just get kind of
[SPEAKER_02]: ...emerged like a, you know, glowing writing on the wall or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a principle that can be taken as far as necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, the Buddha being the foremost of all of the Buddhas in explaining the dhamma, he really explained it to the last every possible detail, which is why the previous Buddha, when he explained the paticca upādāna, he actually didn't go further than nāmarūpa viññāṇa, viññāṇa nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, if you end up
[SPEAKER_02]: If you end the description of the principle, you end with mutual dependence of two things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And two things can be mutually dependent only if they're simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_02]: If two sticks hold each other, which was the simile Sariputta gave for nāmarūpa determining viññāṇa, viññāṇa determining nāmarūpa, they have to be up simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't have now one stick, then put it down, and then leave the other one.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no dependence there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the entire relationship of whichever factor of participant you pick up, is within that nature, shares that nature of simultaneous dependence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a... consciousness is a really important thing, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, before, many Christian people, they believe, like, consciousness is like a self or something, like, that is I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, after, after, actually, knowing the teaching of Venerable Jñānavīla, and then, actually, after meditating, actually, come to see, actually, this consciousness is just, like, supporting the, like, contact to arisen.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's one of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if somebody is out of nibbāna, full understanding, all of the aggregates need to be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, consciousness is that which doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can't see consciousness directly as an object, as you can see a cup, or a glass, or a door, or a car.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just doesn't arise like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why, most often, consciousness is that which people regard as their self.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact that there is something, even if you don't know what it is, that there is a designation which you can call consciousness, you can say, and you can even describe it, means there is something in your experience that stands for that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, full understanding of that would mean full understanding of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't understand consciousness in the same way you would understand objects of your senses, because it precedes them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's because you're conscious, objects of your senses can arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you are not conscious, eyes won't be seeing, ears won't be hearing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's a... it's a... it's a negative phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's... that's why, when I... when I... when I told you before, it's very important to... to recognize this actual and peripheral we spoke, because consciousness is the ultimate peripheral.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's that peripheral that never appears, but it's there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the most precisely you can define it would be in the very ambiguous terms, such as it's the presence.
[SPEAKER_02]: Presence of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that things are present means consciousness is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, people can now overdo that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then end up mystifying consciousness, as the example you gave Christians, or New Age, whatever religion really, including Buddhism, when they say, oh, it's the ultimate consciousness, it's the pure consciousness, it's that consciousness, it's this consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: You over-mystify that presence and then you start talking about presence in itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if there's nothing present, you can't have the presence.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to have a thing in order for it to appear.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why consciousness is not independent.
[SPEAKER_02]: It requires nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there isn't, consciousness could not be discerned.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as much as consciousness determines that which appears, allows it to appear, in the same... to the same extent, that which has appeared defines consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, it wouldn't be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is just of six kinds and...
[SPEAKER_02]: In particular, you don't have to think of them at the same time, because you get complicated things, but you can take a sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eyes, ears, nose.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eyes are conscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ears are conscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, most people automatically assume matter is out there, consciousness is in here.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, matter and consciousness are on the same level.
[SPEAKER_02]: Out there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And their relationship is known as nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that can have the internal aspect and external aspect.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, actually, consciousness is out there with the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why it can never be yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as you think it's in here, you will be taking it as me.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you see it out there, in that material world,
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you realize, well, I cannot have that, nothing more than I could have matter to be mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what Yanira was talking about in slightly different terms, where he was saying that rūpa and viññāṇa, they're, eh... they're like juxt... well, superimposed, or juxtaposed, like two different things, but they come together.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't mix.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, they just get dissociated.
[SPEAKER_02]: The result of that is nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the whole world that you know, that you can never know your past, your future.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within nāmarūpa, within the conscious matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if your consciousness is truly in you, it would be independent from the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when that material body gets disintegrated, consciousness goes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It cannot stay.
[SPEAKER_00]: You mean that, like a...
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the consciousness is in the body, you know, I think... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why would it be?
[SPEAKER_00]: Without consciousness, this body can't... Consciousness is associated with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Associated.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you...
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason you can look in or out, or in and out, or wherever you want, is because you're already conscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that the sense of space, the direction where you look, is possible only because the body is already conscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: The consciousness, the five aggregates are already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it's secondary, it means you can't use it then to find its origin, because it's a result of the origin, not the origin.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you, you know, you look in the distance and you see the tree really really far out, well, your conscience is out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consciousness is out there means that...
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean it's in that matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means it's associated with that matter, no matter how far it is, whether it's in your thoughts or through your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually external.
[SPEAKER_02]: For arahant, all of the aggregates become external.
[SPEAKER_00]: External.
[SPEAKER_02]: None of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: External means... you mean that not self in the... Well, yes, for arahant, yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: External means not self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha did say that for somebody completely free from ignorance, what is left is this conscious body and all whatever name and form externally.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what's left.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the body that is associated with the consciousness or consciousness associated with the body, it's just like two completely different things that kind of come and stop together, which is the birth.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, when one of them goes, the other one cannot remain standing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not that consciousness enters in the body, because any notion of space is a result of the fact that you're conscious.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, consciousness cannot be in its own result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, Arahant said that any idea appears that, like, as my body, but the thought itself, it's not his.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, even when he thinks, my, I, I am, or I'm this, or this is my cup, or whatever, that doesn't imply the emotional significance of me and sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, I can say that's my cup, but if somebody comes to steal it, I won't suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But as a designation of speech, you can, you know, and the Buddha said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, the Tathāgata says, I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't mean that he really thinks he is.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's just a figure of speech becomes for him.
[SPEAKER_02]: Where a Kṛṭṭhūjana, when he says, I am, for him, that is his sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as a designation, it's valid.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to designate it somehow.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just a misunderstanding that goes with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's removed, in case of an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means thought itself is different, actually different, no?
[SPEAKER_02]: I think... Well, different in as much that there is no greed, aversion, delusion, ever, again, to arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't appear.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, they cannot appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he's not just temporarily free from greed, aversion, delusion, an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: He's free from a possibility of those things arising, which is why he's an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, whenever there might be pleasing thoughts, displeasing thoughts, neutral thoughts, but pleasing thoughts won't be inducing any more lust, displeasing thoughts won't be inducing any anger, and neutral thoughts won't be inducing any delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Displeasing, how it happens in the mind environment?
[SPEAKER_02]: Displeasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, this is disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a... it's a feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: I actually didn't understand what... Well, I know, because if you could see the difference, you would be on the way to become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: How can something be displeasing without implying ill will or aversion?
[SPEAKER_02]: If you can see that, then, oh, keep doing it, and then you learn how to be displeased without being angry, which means you free yourself from anger.
[SPEAKER_02]: But...
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't, like, feeling as feeling, for a puthujjana, is not the same when... well, it's not the same as arahant's feeling, as an aggregate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, that's why, when the Buddha would talk, he would make a categorical difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would say, no feeling, in case of an arahant, because there's no puthujjana's feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that doesn't mean that it's just dead.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, that's another putujana's reference, then.
[SPEAKER_02]: And none of the putujana's references can apply to an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not even...
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why, as I said, if, you know, if putujana would understand what a state of arahant is, he would be on the way to become one.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not that you can get a clear idea and still be a putujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: Clear idea frees you from the state of putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the case of Āryas, it's a bit different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's in between.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the overall picture, the fundamental principle, that's all understood, that's all set.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they had to keep repeating it until all the habits, they were based on unwholesome greed, aversion, delusion, disappear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then they can stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're trying to have like a clear definition how far, how much, you can't.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just... Well, the most precise you can get is what the Buddha himself used to describe the four different stages of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in the beginning, they weren't.
[SPEAKER_02]: He didn't... they didn't exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't mean the dhamma didn't exist, or the stages didn't exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was basically somebody who understood the dhamma, and somebody who fully developed it, and now went beyond, and it's free.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then there was that whole chapter in Samyutta Nikāvana, whenever somebody would die, Venerable Ananda would go to the Buddha and ask him, oh, Lord, such and such person died, what's their destination?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then we say, oh, he was
[SPEAKER_02]: He will return one more time, or he won't return at all, or he will be reborn in this heaven, he will be reborn...
[SPEAKER_02]: But it was just becoming all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, well, if whenever somebody dies, you come and ask me about their rebirth, it's just going to be a real bother for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, why don't I tell you something that you can use as a criteria to decide for yourself where most likely that person will be reborn.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, Sotāpanna, at most, will have seven rebirths.
[SPEAKER_02]: He might have less.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not, ah, sotāpati, seven, or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a... it's a guideline.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a... it's like a little stopping point of one, actually, just one process, which is developing, understanding the dhamma, and fully developing that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, you would say, sakadāgāmī would return one more time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Anāgāmī wouldn't return.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, he would give that in relation to the ten fetters.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, by dwelling on those ten fetters, by contemplating them, you can fully understand them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you fully understand them, you understand that you understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's not like, oh, have I understood?
[SPEAKER_02]: It means, ah, there is doubt there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means you haven't understand them enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, sometimes people might, when they get
[SPEAKER_02]: When they overestimate themselves, or are just plain deluded, they refuse to doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they think that's the way to go beyond the doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: When they just do not doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if somebody doubts, they just ignore that.
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody tells them, no, I think, no, no, I refuse to accept that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's, that's just ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_02]: That doesn't, doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you should doubt all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because doubt keeps turning things around.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then,
[SPEAKER_02]: It can make you, it can enable you to develop understanding that will then be truly impenetrable to your full-on acts of doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you never doubt, you don't know if you're beyond the doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you doubt all the time and learn how to, while doubting, go beyond that doubt, ah, then you can truly know for yourself and you cannot doubt that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're doubting and it makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lord Buddha encouraged people to question and doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Venerable Bhārata, you know, actually, not only once, several times, told me that Lord Buddha actually said that we must believe what he said.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you don't actually encourage people to question beliefs.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I think.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you never... No, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, not to question... Oh, yeah, he said, don't take my word for it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, like, don't just believe what I say.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's great for you if you have such faith, but you don't, don't, you don't have to.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, like, you should examine it and see why is it so.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then your faith will be unshakable, because you understood it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because often, yes, you would have... No, no, just don't doubt.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just do what I say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stop asking.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, it was like...
[SPEAKER_02]: He would even encourage monks to keep interrogating each other all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's how you progress.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how you develop understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, sometimes people can take that, oh, well, the Buddha encourages us to doubt and to question, and they mistake that for just being argumentative.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, when somebody just wants to argue over any little point, and then, well, the Buddha, well, no, he didn't say that.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, if you have a genuine interest, you have to keep overturning things and
[SPEAKER_02]: Like digging, digging and digging and digging, whether through conversation with others or inside of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's how understanding can come.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, sometimes people just use that as an excuse to indulge their habits of arguments or just enjoying the debate or things like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he didn't encourage that.
[SPEAKER_02]: He didn't encourage debates for the sake of debates.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, in the history, this is actually, I really wanted to know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think there are arias and arahants that, actually, even from the, even for the photojournalist, you can see clearly, like, it's perfect.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, actually, there are so many cases that in sutras, it's mentioned that there's some arias, like, it's like an immoral or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I actually want, I was wondering this, arahants, some people thought he was angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's no anger in his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How does it happen?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I heard like a very harsh speech and like a... Yeah, that was the case.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, first thing is, it's possible, but it's very unlikely.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you get cases like that, there are a few cases in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or even Venerable Charnam and Sariputta, the one who committed suicide, that Sariputta thought that he wasn't an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when Buddha said, well, why do you say that?
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, oh, because he was associating with bad families, with families of bad reputations.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was very close with them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they all thought bad of him.
[SPEAKER_02]: But Buddha said, no, he was an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the external measure, it's not necessarily a measure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the putusiness criteria cannot encompass an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if they do, it's accidentally.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't know why.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, nevertheless,
[SPEAKER_02]: For, I think, probably for 80 or 90 percent of people, arahant, it means there won't be any of those things left.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think there is some... Well, like in the case of an angry, well, seemingly angry arahant, the Buddha said, oh, the reason why his speech is still like that is for 500 lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_02]: 500 times he was reborn and lived, I don't know, a long time.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, let's just say he lived 80 years each time.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, oh, 4,000?
[SPEAKER_02]: He was reborn in the Brahmin family and they were always higher than the others.
[SPEAKER_02]: They would always speak condescendingly to the others.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the habit just got so established that even when he became an arahant, his aggregates just kept emulating the same form of speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you said that the feeling itself is different for the arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means anger really... Well, there's no anger, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking there was something, a kind of anger, but the thought itself was already disowned.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, again, the only way... the only way you can look at it is through your own... like...
[SPEAKER_02]: Window of experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't really... And you can actually relate to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm sure everyone at some point experienced when some person told you something that you really believed it was like that, and then you realize it was completely different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, while they were saying this, they meant something completely different.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you didn't know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You couldn't know that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in the same sense, when you come across somebody who speaks angrily, you end up assuming he's angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you can find out later on that actually, no, it wasn't an overseas habit.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, if you go again, like, you know, I've been in Thailand, Sri Lanka, so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you see the different cultures, different things people do.
[SPEAKER_02]: And sometimes, something, some things people do in Thailand, it's considered very rude in Europe.
[SPEAKER_02]: And vice versa, something we do in Europe.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know, there can be a different significance of the identical external output.
[SPEAKER_02]: So,
[SPEAKER_02]: You can do something exactly the same in one country, do exactly the same in another country, it can mean completely different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or even coming from the same person.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes you can say something exactly the same and be angry about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes you can say something exactly the same and not be angry about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, anger is indifferent to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Often it's a manifestation of anger, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: act of body, speech or mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if there is no anger, there is still body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they will still be doing things, but it won't be coming from that angle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, are you... is it... is it correct that I was thinking that the ariya means totally...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, like, become indifferent to the any feeling or thought or whatever it arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually, I was... that's why I was thinking that some of the, like, mis... misbehavior of arahanta... not arahanta, ariya,
[SPEAKER_00]: I basically couldn't understand, because I think any kind of such unwholesome thought, whatever, in the case of ārya, not arahant, just then ārya means totally indifferent to such feelings.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Totally indifferent would be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Totally indifferent means equanimous.
[SPEAKER_02]: That would be fully developed upekha.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's totally different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Forty thousand, by the way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in case of an Ārya, again, it depends on how far his faculties developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you know, when... well, there was that sutta when the Buddha was staying in that forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: And on the other side of that forest, there was a group of young men and women.
[SPEAKER_02]: They paid those courtesans to come with them in the forest, so, you know, they were all getting loose and sensual, and then they all fell asleep after, and one of them woke up, one of the courtesans woke up, and stole all of their gold and money, and ran away.
[SPEAKER_02]: When they realize, they start chasing her.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, imagine their state of mind after this pleasure sensual evening and then full of anger over like, oh, we've been deceived and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: They were chasing to kill her, most likely.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then they accidentally, as they were chasing, came across the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: They didn't even know he was the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, he told them, well, why don't you sit down and I can teach you something instead.
[SPEAKER_02]: It will be more beneficial to you than finding that gold.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you know, I'm sure some of them calmed down, but still...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm pretty sure they were still angry.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Lenov said...
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, right there and then, he calmed them down.
[SPEAKER_02]: First, he talked about the significance of virtue, why it's good to develop, and generosity.
[SPEAKER_02]: They understood that, because everybody can understand that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that was a sufficient basis for them to then develop right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because then he spoke about the dhamma, and they understood exactly what he meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And they all became sotāpānas.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize, oh, okay, it's not that hard then.
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody can have their mind full of lust, and then aversion, and anger, and then they could calm down, and then they could see the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that doesn't oblige them to follow it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they might have well understood it, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it comes from their previous lives.
[SPEAKER_02]: They have maybe practiced some... Well, I think what comes from previous life is the fact that you're born as human, with all of your faculties intact.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing else excuses somebody for not understanding dhamma or understanding it.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, those who make the effort will understand, those who don't, they won't.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, there is sometimes previous lives, but I think people put too much emphasis on that as a way of absolving themselves from responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you are a born, intelligent, normal human being who can think normally, discern normally, there is no excuse for not understanding dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: There just isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything is there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you don't understand, it's because you haven't been making the right effort.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's it's it's kind of blunt, but that's that's exactly how it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, or when you had those, like, when sometimes the householders would come and see the Buddha and or even come to to complain about something or criticize him,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he would come and down, talk about dhamma, and then they would understand him and become sotāpannas.
[SPEAKER_02]: And sometimes they would say, oh, from now on, I want to become a monk and practice this.
[SPEAKER_02]: But sometimes they wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sometimes they would say, well, thank you, Lord.
[SPEAKER_02]: We are very busy.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have to go back home.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have lots of things to attend to.
[SPEAKER_02]: As sotāpannas.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like his father.
[SPEAKER_02]: When his father came and complained about Rākula, because he ordained him, he came all in tears and upset.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, first you went, now you took my only grandson.
[SPEAKER_02]: But
[SPEAKER_02]: Through explaining the dhamma, and then, oh, thank you very much, I could go now, I'm busy.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, they don't necessarily always want to practice it, especially because, oh, this understanding is already quite an accomplishment, and they get content in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which means that three quarters of their mind still needs to be
[SPEAKER_02]: So to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not that clear, clear-cut, but in the nutshell, they understood what needs to be done, but they don't necessarily want to do it right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: They will eventually.
[SPEAKER_02]: They can't ignore it for too long.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why Sotāpanna said, at most, seven rebirths.
[SPEAKER_02]: No more than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that... and even... even that the whole, as I said before, the whole division of satipaṭṭhāna, sakadāgāmī, anāgāmī and arahant, sometimes the Buddha would omit sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_02]: He would just say satipaṭṭhāna and then he would start talking about anāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he would talk about arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as I said in the beginning, there were no.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was just fully enlightened or not fully enlightened.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's... it's a guideline.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a guideline, basically, of understanding the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it was also a guideline given to people to reassure them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just recently, I came again across that sutta of Mahānāma, the householder, who was... it wasn't clear in the suttas whether he was sakadāgāmī or sotāpāna, because he was never said.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was always said that he's a noble disciple, who still lives the household life.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there was this sutta when he says,
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he knew that he was a... well, he knew that he was a noble disciple, but it was before the Buddha defined all of these seven rebirths or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he came to the Buddha one night, one evening, and he said, oh, how is it loaded?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like,
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, I'm the one who understood the dhamma, and I know that I understood it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But on some occasions, when I walk on the... like now, when I come to see the Lord in the evening, and it's getting dark, and if I come across a stray dog, a stray man, or a stray elephant, or some form of danger, he forgets about all the dhamma he understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, he gets filled with fear.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he says, what if I were to die at that moment, on account of that stray dog, stray elephant, stray man, what will my destination be?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he was concerned that if he dies in that state of mind, although he knew that he was a noble disciple, he was concerned that if he dies in that state of mind, his destination might be unfortunate.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because unless you have a supernatural power, you can't see those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha said, oh, you have absolutely nothing to fear.
[SPEAKER_02]: The one who understood the dhamma, who developed that kind of noble virtue, noble understanding, know what it is?
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if your mind is overwhelmed with fear, when you die, it still won't make a difference to your destination.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the interesting bit to me, then, is that, oh, there was a Sotāpanna or Sakadāgāmī, who wasn't sure about certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: He was sure about the nature of the dhamma, but he doesn't know
[SPEAKER_02]: How far his understanding of that dhamma, the real understanding of the dhamma, how far takes him?
[SPEAKER_02]: And for that, the Buddha would often talk like, I will see the mountain Himalayas and then he would pick up seven grains of sand and said, the size of that mountain is the size of suffering that Sotāpanna has abandoned and all he has left is the amount of this
[SPEAKER_02]: Seven grains of sand.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how much he has destroyed.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's quite an accomplishment even to get that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why he would give those encouragements of that kind.
[SPEAKER_02]: But Sotāpanna doesn't see that.
[SPEAKER_02]: He doesn't, you know...
[SPEAKER_02]: He sees the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: He sees the timeless principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: He sees the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_02]: He sees the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And actually, that in itself is more than enough.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of this comes in as an extra.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the arahants, they don't remember their previous life?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sariputta couldn't remember any of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, like, the foremost, after the Buddha, in teaching the dharma and expounding every angle and approach, just, you know, people couldn't see the difference whether he would speak or the Buddha, because he was just... he understood all of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But he said he couldn't see even a little goblin.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: He couldn't see any of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Neither supernatural nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was just non-existent for him.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why it's irrelevant whether you see it or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: Some people can, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking that remembering the past, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's very important to understand the role of karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not necessary.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, karma...
[SPEAKER_02]: If karma is truly determined by your past, you're stuck.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: If Angulimala's karma was in his past, he couldn't have not overcome it, because he couldn't bring those people back to life.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Action is intention, and intention is very present thing, and things you do are very present, and that's where you abandon it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And when you abandon your... through, like, fully understanding, through abandoning ignorance, when you abandon your action by body, speech or mind, nothing you have done, nothing you would have done, can pertain to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the same sense, when you abandon the nature of present, what's present,
[SPEAKER_02]: You abandon past, that can be present.
[SPEAKER_02]: You abandon future, that can be present.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you abandon present, that's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it's important for them to understand vipāka.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because karma, I think the whole notion got overly mystified now.
[SPEAKER_02]: It almost becomes like this energy of of of righteousness, like, well, that's your karma, you deserve it, or things like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But karma means action.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, filling this cup with water is a form of karma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Wholesome or unwholesome... People might want to dwell on vipāka, on the results of that kamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's something that can cause sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you start thinking, well, like, you know, if I misbehave, if I do these things, I could end up experiencing very bad results.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then that can inspire them to be more wholesome and do less evil or whatever they were doing before.
[SPEAKER_02]: But in terms of thinking about karma and like understanding the workings of the karma or something like that, the Buddha said it can only bring madness or distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless you're a Buddha, who can then fully understand the workings of the karma, if he directs his mind towards it,
[SPEAKER_02]: If somebody else tries, you just end up distracting yourself about pointless things, or go mad on account of really trying to understand something that you cannot possibly comprehend.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which, another, it just says it in a different way, that's irrelevant, in terms of understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you understand the nature of action, you abandon it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't understand
[SPEAKER_02]: Why, when you've done something in the past, now that was the result of this... That's a complete, like, looking elsewhere in a wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: How would the Buddha teach the importance to be virtuous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Virtue... How would he teach that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, he would teach that because of the...
[SPEAKER_02]: He would say about the vipāka, he would say about the results.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you mean... And then, again, even then, he said, well, don't believe what I say, but reflect for yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think Amāli said before, when he told those people,
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, but it's a fact that you don't know whether there is a next life or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a matter of belief.
[SPEAKER_02]: You might take it or you might not.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, even then, you can use your intelligence.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even Pratyujana can understand that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whereby, he can just basically sit and think, okay, I don't know that there is a future life or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I misbehave here, right now, in this life,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, I'll get in trouble from people.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a fact.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll be put in jail.
[SPEAKER_02]: People will hate me.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I get away with it, people won't trust me.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to be on the run.
[SPEAKER_02]: I have to keep looking around all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll live in fear, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's all unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if there is a future life, then he'll experience even worse rebirth on account of bad actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is no future life, okay, he won't experience any bad rebirth, but he'll still suffer in this life on account of his bad actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, the other person who thinks, well, if I do good in this life, well, people will praise me, which is nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: People will be helpful to me, which is nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: People will want to repay my kindness, which is nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: People will trust me, which is nice.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, if there is no future life, well, so be it.
[SPEAKER_02]: At least, I live a good life here.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there is a future life, then I'll also get a better rebirth.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I win on both fronts.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if I misbehave, I lose on both fronts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even then, it doesn't have to be a matter of belief anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a clear understanding and almost a practical.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, oh, so it's actually... that's why this is wholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why that's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why it's better to behave than to misbehave.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, they have no knowledge of previous lives, no knowledge of future, vipāka, waiting for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just intelligence, human intelligence, basic discerning.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just stop and think for a second and it becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there's no denying that if you do unwholesome things, people will complain.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you meet someone who can't stop doing wrong doing, how, how, how, how it can...
[SPEAKER_00]: Some, some people, they're supposing in front of me, keep killing the snakes and all of those things, and it's impossible for them to stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: How, how, how do you... No, they're lying, they're lying to themselves.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they say it's impossible, means... What that means, doesn't mean it's impossible, means they can't be bothered to try to stop.
[SPEAKER_02]: So they'll keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you can't stop it if they don't want to stop it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unless you're stronger than them and twist their arm and restrain them until the snake escapes.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't do it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you never give any advice?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, there isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, you could.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, you can...
[SPEAKER_02]: If you try to convince people too hard, they will start ignoring you even harder.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, unless the person who's just done something silly, unwholesome in front of you,
[SPEAKER_02]: He's not willing to listen to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No amount of things you say, and you'll be wasting your words then.
[SPEAKER_02]: They won't take any heed.
[SPEAKER_02]: If they come and, oh, yeah, okay, well, like, if they really want to understand, then it's a different matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you can tell them just what I told you now.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, even if you don't know whether your bad action will bring the future misery in terms of the future rebirth,
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you can still know for sure that in this life it will.
[SPEAKER_02]: And also, the fact is that you don't know whether you're going to be reborn or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: Surely, you should play it safe, as if you are going to be reborn.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, just in case, I'll behave here.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'll be praised here on my behavior.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, if there is a future rebirth, then I'll be safe.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's almost like a precaution, just in case I'll behave.
[SPEAKER_02]: If I know for sure that there is no life, this is the only life, yeah, I'll do whatever I like.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you cannot know that for sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's something you can know.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can know for sure that you don't know these things for sure, and you can never will.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why it's better to, you know, use wisdom and say, well, why would I, like, risk?
[SPEAKER_02]: There's no...
[SPEAKER_02]: Especially when we're not risking, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: behaving properly, will earn me respect in this life, and protect me in the future life, if there is one,
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a winner in every respect.
[SPEAKER_02]: But people usually say, well, I don't know that there is a rebirth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yeah, but you don't know that there isn't a rebirth either.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they don't think that far.
[SPEAKER_02]: They just think the first part, because that means, oh, well, I don't believe that I can do what I want here.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, even if you don't believe or believe, if you stop and think, it will become apparent why you shouldn't be doing those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, again, unless a person is willing to hear that, he won't listen to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't listen to anybody.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, yes, sometimes people come and ask him the wrong question, or they would formulate the question wrongly.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said that sometimes Tathāgata meets this person and Tathāgata has inclination to teach him, but then this misguided person formulates his question wrongly, and then Tathāgata goes silent.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he doesn't want to teach him that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because they came from a wrong place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because whatever he says, they'll take it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or sometimes, they come with a question and ask him, like when they ask him, oh, Master Gautama, is there a self?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you say, yes, there is, there isn't, that person will take that not-self as self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he already implied in his question that there is a self.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, which one is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the Buddha was quiet.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well, does that mean there isn't, or there is, or isn't, or both, or neither?
[SPEAKER_02]: And he was just quiet.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then this person left.
[SPEAKER_02]: And Ānanda, Venerable Ānanda asked him, well, why didn't you answer?
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, well, because whatever I would have said, he would have misunderstood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he was coming with a completely wrong attitude.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he wasn't willing to understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, I think, on a later occasion, when Ānanda told him, you should ask like this, not, don't ask like that,
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when he asked rightly, the Tathāgata taught him, and then he understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was actually a big surprise, before the... Venerable Garapānyu, he first time told me that there is no self is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before, always I heard that all monks, they keep, there is no self, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's a denial.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is quite...
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually didn't notice my mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he told, he told me that in the case of the general, it's impossible to say that there is no self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But why many monks they don't know in Sīla?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because they are putujanas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, maybe.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, if somebody's not a putujana, they wouldn't be saying that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not written in sutra that for putujana we can't say that there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing written in sutra.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, putujana should see through the nature of his self that it cannot be his, and that's why it becomes not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means not-myself.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think that's... that's not just... that's everywhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the West, in Thailand, everywhere.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not just in Sri Lanka.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because when anybody comes across Buddhism on the superficial terms, that's the first thing you come across.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ah, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then that negative, like, becomes your self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yes, I don't believe in self.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's my self-belief.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's much harder than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said before, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You actually have to first see what your self is, in order to stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a very different thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why you have atta, and then you have anatta.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, not no-self, but not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that which is taken as self, and then understood as not-self, is still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That thing doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when you say no-self, you just deny the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In foreign, there is self, but it's not self.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is that, which used to be taken as self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Used to be.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now there is no-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: No-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, it's not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every experience of an Arahant is not-self.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean that eight putkarā and then one puttu, puttu jhāna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it means what I said before.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's... it's only... it was only defined later.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the commentary and the interpretation of those mind moments, when you kind of want to and then you enter into the... you enter the path, then you realize the fruit, the next moment is... it's just lots of nonsense.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the suttas means... And again, even that division came from the Buddha, from somebody who had such vision, but people might not know that necessarily for themselves, or for others.
[SPEAKER_02]: When Sariputra couldn't recognize another ant.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is another sutta, I think, I might have mentioned before, about Venerable Padiya, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: The Dwarf.
[SPEAKER_02]: You've been mocked at.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: You told me that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: In Udanas, when Sariputra was teaching this monk,
[SPEAKER_02]: So he actually didn't have any work to do anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that wasn't apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: In sutra, clearly, it's written that eight, eight pūkarā, one pūkarā.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no, it's clearly written in terms of, again, as it's clearly written that there are, like, four stages of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha talked about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha said that there is a somebody, there is a difference, like, within, within somebody who is a sotāpanna, there is a difference between somebody who fully realized that he's a sotāpanna and somebody who didn't quite yet realize that he's actually a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, you develop understanding of the Four Noble Truths, for example.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you understood it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But now, the benefits of that understanding have not become apparent yet.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the difference between the path and the fruit.
[SPEAKER_02]: For some people, they understood it, and they understood it so hard, that the benefits are pretty much immediate.
[SPEAKER_02]: For others, they are not.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what the Buddha said in relation to that is that if somebody has understood, like in case of Sotāpanna, somebody understood the dhamma, the benefits will have to be reached, if not before, then at the moment of its death.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's not... nothing kind of magical or mystical.
[SPEAKER_02]: It simply means that nature of understanding of the dhamma basically goes through the nature of death.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you understood that, when those aggregates do start falling apart, you will fall apart through that understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's what you have understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is why, at the moment of death, the latest, you will get the benefits of your understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the same for for any of the Arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether it's a Sotāpanna and his fruit, Sakadāgāmī and his fruit, or Anāgāmī and his fruit, or Arahant and his fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a clear line between Anāgāmī and Arahant, or Sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there isn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, there isn't a clear line at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why there's that Sutta when all those monks came, I don't know, hundreds of them, and they all declared Arahantship.
[SPEAKER_02]: And somebody asked the Buddha, is that really the case?
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, some of them are truly arahants, but some of them overestimated themselves and they're still anāgāmīs.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he didn't like, you know, they were not like putujanas, completely deluded, thinking they're arahants.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, they were anāgāmīs, thinking they were arahants.
[SPEAKER_00]: He could distinguish it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for Lord Buddha, there's a clear line between anāgāmī and ānāgāmī?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because he was the Sāma, Sambuddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only he can.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, only he can, or sometimes people who had ability to see other people's minds, with a special ability, they could see.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that was, you know, random.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was not a guarantee.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so, so that is the meaning of eight-pākara.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the line is not clear.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's, it's basically, as I said, it's a, it's a one development.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why somebody can become an arahant in the first watch of the night.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't mean... it's the same path they walk.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just how fast they walk it and whether they stop at the resting stops or not.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's one path.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same path.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like trying to achieve four different things or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even those four different things are sometimes three different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: When he omitted sakadāgāmī from the descriptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or if you read in the Sānyūtanikaya about... like you think, okay, anāgāmī means rebirth in pure abodes.
[SPEAKER_02]: But there is a whole chapter in Sānyūtanikaya about anāgāmīs.
[SPEAKER_02]: There are like hundreds of different
[SPEAKER_02]: realms within the pure abodes, whereby the anāgāmīs would be reborn, depending on how big anāgāmīs they were.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's just like... it's... it's... it's... well, it's kind of irrelevant in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's relevant in a sense of abandoning the ten fetters, and that's something some people can contemplate and practice in regard to.
[SPEAKER_02]: How far and what rebirth, unless there's supernatural powers or unless you live with the Buddha or somebody like that, it will be a distraction.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's not, it's not, it's not directly related to the practice of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can be an encouragement, if it comes from... Well, again, you don't need to have somebody now.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you read the suttas, you'll see what the Buddha was saying in relation to people who attained this or this or this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to know that... what did you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: You said that what I see, Babalu, in the mind, you said that that is the thought, thought of sound, the thought of sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a thought?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, five senses are known for what they are because of your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: They all meet in your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And because of that, the mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like the
[SPEAKER_02]: Because in the first verse of Dhammapada, the mind is the forerunner of all things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, if you, like, if you have an object of your sight, again, if you look at a flask in front of you, see, you can't just have a pure sight, because even colors are distinguished as different colors.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, your eyes cannot distinguish... like, if your eyes would operate without your mind, it would... well, it's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even think like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, when you look at the flask, there is already a significance implied in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is already a thought of flask.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you know... don't know the name, don't know what it is, there is a thought of object being seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before... before I heard, eh... just after the... with consciousness, the external object, an internal sense organ, with the help of consciousness, the contact arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that sight is called feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perception means that this... this is... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Perception means perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't feel your perception.
[SPEAKER_02]: You feel your feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling... what... suppose it depends.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, I look at this flask.
[SPEAKER_00]: What kind of feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe nothing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Maybe neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if it's perhaps something, I don't know, something very significant that some person gave you, and if you look at that, then the feeling will arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it doesn't always... That's the thing, like, feeling has its own domain, perception has its own domain.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you want to understand it correctly, you have to start applying that understanding to those domains correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, if I ask you, how do you feel now?
[SPEAKER_02]: There has to be a feeling there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can say, oh, I feel all right, which is a form of pleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can say, well, I don't feel that well, I'm a bit tired, which is a form of unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can say, I feel neutral.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that situation, a general situation of you sitting here in this kuti, talking on dhamma, that is already something that you're perceiving, peripherally, in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's present, because if I ask you, where are you now?
[SPEAKER_02]: You will immediately know where you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't have to stop and figure out, because it's already there, so you just have to access it with your attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, if you forget about that, which is where actually, where it should start.
[SPEAKER_02]: The contemplation has to start at the most general level you're capable of.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you don't know that, then you will take a random object and try to examine it, almost scientifically or psychologically, and then try to discover the nature of perception and nature of feeling.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I look at this thing in my hands.
[SPEAKER_02]: What do I feel?
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if you gain any understanding from that, it will be on the level of intellectual satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yes, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: But leaves the whole domain of feeling and perception on the general level absolutely intact.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in other words, you have to start from the opposite direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to think you are here, away from home, in this kuti, talking about dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you can define it whichever way you are.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's your current situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that situation, there are objects around you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within those objects, there are more particular objects, there are more important objects, there are less important objects, there are more useful objects, like that cushion, there are less useful objects, like that bed, that you don't need anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's all within that experience as a whole of you being in this room, sitting down and talking.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that was that the mindfulness of the body postures works on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're aware of your body posture, that's almost like the most general thing that determines your current situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that situation is perceived, that situation is felt, that situation is intended.
[SPEAKER_02]: On the level of that situation is where the contact happens.
[SPEAKER_02]: And only because you're already contacted, you can distinguish all these particular things around you, with your eyes, ears, nose, and so on.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, on that general situation, is where the three meet.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they don't meet like
[SPEAKER_02]: Cause and effect.
[SPEAKER_02]: As often the commentaries interpret, we say you have one hand, another hand, you have the sense organs, and the consciousness, and they meet, and the sound is the sound, or whatever it was.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, the sound is the contact, doesn't it?
[SPEAKER_02]: I forgot, it was a long time ago.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, the point is, the point is, they don't meet like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, even that nature of meeting is timeless.
[SPEAKER_02]: It does not involve time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Clapping hands involve time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can put it as simply as that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Saḷāyatana is part of the paticca upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever is part of paticca upādāna shares the principle of paticca upādāna.
[SPEAKER_02]: Otherwise, it wouldn't be included there.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it means that conscious matter is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Conscious matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if...
[SPEAKER_02]: Things come in range, as the Buddha said, the corresponding engagement occurs.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't occur always.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if things come in range, that can be the cause for the contact.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then also, consciousness and the working sense organs, i.e.
[SPEAKER_02]: matter, are required.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if something happens to them, there won't be any sight arising, there won't be any hearing or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: If your ear organs are damaged or whatever, even while you're still alive, that's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: They'll stop working.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, like, there is... the Buddha did refer to a thing called āyur-saṅkhāra, that upon which life depends, like vitality.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, sometimes you can be brain dead, that the body can be almost completely dysfunctional, but not quite.
[SPEAKER_02]: And for as long as it's not quite, there might be still some vitality left in the body, in which case people wake up from the coma or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But sometimes they just don't.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or there is a state of cessation of perception and feeling, where breathing stops.
[SPEAKER_02]: In meditation, it's just the ultimate form of development of your mind, whereby, like, you don't even breathe.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the didas, the buddha, uh, no, sorry, it was the nun, dhamma dīna, when her ex, when her husband came to visit her, and she taught him, and he became sotāpanna, and he asked, what's the difference between somebody who is dead and somebody who is in cessation and perception of feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, the difference is that the one who is in such an observational feeling, he still has his life vitality left.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, he returns, he re-emerges.
[SPEAKER_02]: The dead person doesn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's almost like on the level of metaphysics.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, the relationship between consciousness and body is external.
[SPEAKER_02]: Consciousness is not internal in the body.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I think the Buddha compared in the suttas like a ember, like a gem.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if there is a thread running clearly through the gem, that's like conscious body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they are completely two different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thread is not part of the gem.
[SPEAKER_02]: Gem is not part of the thread.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just that it's entrapped in the gem.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what Yanavira referred to, actually.
[SPEAKER_02]: He didn't say that body and consciousness are superimposed.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said they're juxtaposed.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means they're completely indifferent to each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just... it's just an occurrence of them coming together, but not... not merging together.
[SPEAKER_02]: They come together, and as a result of that overlap, you get nāmarūpa, that which you can designate.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can never directly access matter, nor can you ever directly access consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can abandon matter by fully understanding it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sorry, by fully understanding consciousness, you remove the footing for the matter.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you stop misunderstanding that overlap of conscious body.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, well, it helped me and I think it's probably more helpful because everybody, by default, assumes consciousness is inside.
[SPEAKER_02]: And everything else is external.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I did actually remember that.
[SPEAKER_02]: I didn't make much out of it at the time, but when I was reading Existential Philosophy, Sartre, and they were talking in terms of things were being... like, not things are conscious, in terms of that they have... that that matter has consciousness in it, but no, their consciousness is out there with the things, not in them.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, that's why you have six types of consciousness, because you have six senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Every sense discerns things out there, and the only reason it can discern is because consciousness is there with those things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the conscious matter, and then, if there is ignorance present,
[SPEAKER_02]: When that contact arises, well, the contact will arise as a result of you feeling contacted.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you appropriate a contact, then you're contacted.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, contact always pertains to sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you see that thing out there, already arisen, that the contact is better, means, oh, you can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't prevent consciousness from disassociating from the matter, if it decides to do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Which is, I think, what happens when sometimes people lose their mind and they go catatonic.
[SPEAKER_02]: They go completely, like, dead, motionless.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nor can you prevent that matter to be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_02]: You absolutely no... You can't even conceive having said in it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just beyond your range.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, your entire life depends upon it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the perilous situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you realize that your consciousness is as external as this matter that you see, and you have no say in it, then it ceases to be yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when corresponding engagement occurs, you see that occurring as a result of things, that you have no say in it, therefore, whatever occurs on their account, you have no say in that either.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this experience, in these episodes, how does it happen?
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people think that there's a body in the... Well, I don't... yeah, hard to say, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite a...
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm sure something happens, but people use words differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: They say they saw their body, but without any eyes, they can't... Yeah, yeah, I'd say that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't believe.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not... it's like... As I say, it's hard to know what people mean when they describe these things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, you know, they might use certain words that will mean something for you, something else for them.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when they say, I saw my body, you know, it might have well been a thought of their body, a thought of them abandoning the body, but because it was a real life and death experience, that thought was very significant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was so real, as they would usually describe it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It was as real as if I was looking at my body over there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can be that, or who knows, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, when people even try to explain mundane things, often misunderstanding happens, because you realize they're using the same words you know, but completely differently.
[SPEAKER_02]: They meant something completely different.
[SPEAKER_02]: Imagine when you try to explain such personal things, or like, when people try to talk about, you know, the spiritual thoughts or whatever else, and he gets all like, what?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't make sense out of it, because what it means for them doesn't necessarily mean other things to others.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that... that's exactly why the Buddha did refer to the miracle of teaching.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said, if a person who understood the dhamma is able to convey that to another, and then they understand it, that's... that equals a miracle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the dhamma is so personal.
[SPEAKER_02]: The sense itself, the senses and everything, that there is no way that when I say something in regard to senses, another person will think exactly the same thing, unless we're both arahants or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it's so personal that the meaning of it is so personal.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it really needs to be... you need to dig through it and see what it's meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, I think Amāli said before, again, it's like when I said, well, you can just take these five aggregates, Pali terms,
[SPEAKER_02]: rūpa, vedanā, sañña, saṅkhāra, viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just take the English words, or Japanese words for that, and think about it, and see how much of it do you actually understand.
[SPEAKER_02]: I remember when I was reading the suttas and reading consciousness, and you just really know you have consciousness, but then you stop once and think, well, okay, forget about the Pali, forget about the sutta, just use the word consciousness, that I think I know,
[SPEAKER_02]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, when I say consciousness, what is that, that this designation consciousness stands for, in my experience?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize, okay, consciousness is very hard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why don't I start with easy matter?
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you realize that's equally hard.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, what is that matter then?
[SPEAKER_02]: And you realize, if you were to fully understand these five designations, you would be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there is no difference between intellectual understanding or real understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Understanding is understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can start intellectually or non-intellectually, but understanding that it's the same arrival.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you might start pondering about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And as long as you're not doing like scholastic comparison between the words and its roots, if you're really trying to see what designation consciousness stands in your experience,
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just... That's why in the suttas, if you read something, when they say a thing twice, when they say, first jhāna, first jhāna, what is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or they say something else, they repeat it twice.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's basically a way of bringing it to the mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then to see that, that you just brought to your mind, in your experience, for what it stands for.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just kind of examine this code and explain it, or draw the parallel, do the drawing, or whatever, a scheme.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, like, really understand if consciousness-consciousness that I just said, what is that what I said?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is it that this saying stands for?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_02]: What did I just designate, in my experience, when I said feeling?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is feeling now that I said it?
[SPEAKER_02]: And the fact that you said feeling, means it stands for something.
[SPEAKER_02]: It designates something.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you really have to push as hard as... well, as far as you need to, until same feeling stands for that which feeling really is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not for your idea of what feeling is, or for your misunderstanding of what feeling is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can see how many people have not understood this,
[SPEAKER_02]: By seeing how many people cannot distinguish between what they perceive and what they feel, or what they intend.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it's all like a like a like a jungle.
[SPEAKER_02]: Just everything and everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember that you sent me that like a notes on meditation, something, your disciple wrote something there, notes on notes on meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that was dukkha, on dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was written that the difference, the perception, the difference between the arahant and the kutu-jana is that arahant, when he sees the chair, he doesn't think it is his.
[SPEAKER_00]: But kutu-jana thinks it is his chair.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only that is the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it's slightly subtler than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: He might not think that's my chair, because if it's his chair, I won't think it's my chair.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I can think that chair is for me to sit on.
[SPEAKER_00]: For me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's for me to sit on.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the chair, the significance of the chair, is for sitting.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's to be sat on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that doesn't necessarily mean sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: But when somebody who holds sense of self and self-view approaches it, he will inevitably take it like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when a patujana sees a chair, or any other signi... a cup,
[SPEAKER_02]: To drink water from?
[SPEAKER_02]: It will be... a cup is for my eye to drink water from.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's for myself, for me, to drink water from.
[SPEAKER_02]: The chair is for me to sit on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's already a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: For me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put... you put
[SPEAKER_00]: What's happening?
[SPEAKER_00]: I never think that it's my river.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's fine, but as I said, seeing the river outside, it's only a particular object within the general situation that you're in, and yourself is on the general level.
[SPEAKER_02]: You'll never see your sense of self on the level where you're seeing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Your sense of self is in that peripheral situation that determines everything particular that's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why people never... can never understand anatta when they go about and say, ah, that's not real, that doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_02]: See, it's so constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_02]: I just destroyed it.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_02]: Those are all objects of your senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: And your sense of self is way deeper than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's on the level of that situation I was telling you about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you are standing here from which way... from... from... from which position you can see the river out there.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's already something you perceive as one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's one thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Very general thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And your sense of self is on that level.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's where it has to be understood.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you look at the river out there and start looking at your sense of self there, then you already forgot half of the image.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean that you said that because of sense of self,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I think that, like, from contact, feeling arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: The next perception arises, the next mental formation.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see it as process.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, he doesn't think, like, from contact.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that process, as I said before, it's not really a process like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can't think one, two, three, four, five, like, occurring one after the other.
[SPEAKER_02]: When ignorance, there is contact.
[SPEAKER_02]: When ignorance, contact.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's all you can say.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means, the only... like, if the contact is manifest, means ignorance is present there, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as contact is being manifested.
[SPEAKER_02]: Contact, you mean... mean being touched by things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even for arahants, they have contact?
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, they don't have ignorance.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, there is nothing to be contacted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contact, what do you mean by contact?
[SPEAKER_02]: Being touched.
[SPEAKER_02]: Means having... Not necessarily, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_02]: As you see, you can be very indifferent over the external objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: You care about the flask, I don't care about the river.
[SPEAKER_02]: I don't care about anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still be able to, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Arahants, they haven't done everything properly on the level of that situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, if you're not... if there is no sense of self,
[SPEAKER_02]: On the most general level, of Michael sitting in a cave kuti, leaning on the cushion, talking about the dhamma, that's one experience, very general.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can define it as far as you want, it still remains one experience, as a whole, general.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you abandon that, then whatever comes in front of you, particularly, pleasing or displeasing,
[SPEAKER_02]: Abandoning or what do you mean by that?
[SPEAKER_02]: Fully understanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not regarding as yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Okay, let's try this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Michael indicated...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not easy.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not easy to understand, so you don't have to... yeah, you don't have to worry about it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, maybe a little bit, because it can keep you going, but... Michael indicated living in the cushion, talking about the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: That... like, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: But not just a thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a thought that stands for your actual experience right now, which means it's a very general experience, very real as such.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can stop there now, because that situation remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whether we talk quickly or slowly or stop talking for a moment, it's still Mayuko in the cave, leaning on the cushion, talking about the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in that sense, it's independent of the particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even if you move the cushion, if you're not leaning on the cushion, it's still, generally, Mayuko in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within Mayuko sitting in the cave, she leans on the cushion.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how it's hierarchically ordered.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you don't have to understand all of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can take one of those levels, like, I'm... which is the body posture.
[SPEAKER_02]: I'm being seated right now.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a general, general thought that stands for your actual body posture.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can establish your mindfulness upon that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, see, the thing is, Michael in the cave, sitting on the floor, talking dhamma, is the fundamental situation you're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you look at it, would it be possible for you to sit in this cave, that you can see now, if there is no cave here?
[SPEAKER_02]: Or if somebody destroys it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Would it be possible for you to sit on the floor and lean on the cushion, if I take the cushion?
[SPEAKER_02]: You wouldn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you realize that these objects of your senses, things you can actually see and hear and touch,
[SPEAKER_02]: In that indirect manner, not directly like this is not mine, this is not mine, but in that indirect manner, they indicate that that situation as a whole, the general mindful picture, is not independent.
[SPEAKER_02]: It depends upon these very particular objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if they are removed at any point, this general situation cannot remain standing.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the utmost general situation is your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: The Buddha said the whole world is within your body.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if your body is removed, your whole world goes.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if the body goes, the one you can see, you can see in the mirror, like you can see in others, if that's taken, none of the general situation, none of the most loftier feelings or thoughts can remain standing.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's the relationship between peripheral and actual.
[SPEAKER_02]: I was telling you about the needs to be understood, because that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you forget about the peripheral, general, you just end up chasing these particular objects.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you're not seeing them correctly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't see them as mutually determining the general situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just see them in a very linear manner, which is on the level of science,
[SPEAKER_02]: scholastics or, I don't know, medicine, any form of like, like, like natural thing, psychology, all of that is just linear observation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it doesn't reveal the timeless principle of mutual dependence.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's upādana.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because for as long as the cave is present, your situation of being in the cave
[SPEAKER_02]: can be maintained.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, vice versa.
[SPEAKER_02]: If there was no intention for you to be in the cave in the first place, this particular cave you see, you wouldn't have come here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Therefore, you wouldn't have seen it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, as much as the particular things determine your general situation, general situation defines the particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in terms of the practice of mindfulness, works along those levels.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you have a thought, no matter how distant, but even a little bit present in the back of your mind, that you are in this cave, if that's established as an anchor, what I said before, whatever you do while you're in the cave, you'll be mindful of it, without having to trace every particular thing you do while you're in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you can anchor yourself in being seated on the floor.
[SPEAKER_02]: Whatever you do, whatever you think, whatever you say, while you remain seated on the floor, if you're established upon the thought of being seated on the floor, you'll be mindful of whatever you do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because mindfulness is about not chasing these particular things, but being established in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you don't have to, like, strain yourself in terms of always seeing it, because it's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just have to remember and step back into it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because your situation of sitting on the floor in a cave is already there, and it's still there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And even if you stop thinking about it, it's still there, because the body is still in that situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's why you can re-establish mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the more skilled you become, the quicker you re-establish it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The more skilled you become in recognizing the things that you can use to establish your mindfulness on.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's a very different type of practice than what you get in the Burmese retreat centers, where you're all about focusing and studying and observing and trying to catch the particular moment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's as unmindful as you can get.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you end up forcing yourself into that more and more, which is why all those people get very intense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means that you...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to worry so much about what's healing or what is positive or what is... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you can, if that... if you choose that as an approach, but you don't have to understand everything at once, all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: You need to develop mindfulness to the extent necessary where understanding is developed to a sufficient degree where you don't take things to be yours anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't mean that you actually have to go around destroying things or giving things up.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, oh, take this because it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: It wasn't yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how can you even give it away?
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and again, you can be mindful in regard to any of the feeling, perception or intentions through this form of mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're mindful, seated of your situation and your body posture, and then feeling arises while you're seated in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's your mindful regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, you can choose feeling to be the anchor of your mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: You say, I'm feeling this way now.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I feel like that, through that, I'm feeling this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Through that, I'm feeling that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why in Ānāpānasati Sutta, the Buddha said, when he was talking about
[SPEAKER_02]: In the development of mindfulness, he said, while breathing in like this, I feel like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: While breathing in like that, I'll observe my whole body.
[SPEAKER_02]: While breathing in, breathing out, breathing in, breathing both, I will experience my body in this way.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will feel this.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will feel pleasure.
[SPEAKER_02]: I will feel... while, while, while.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you actually do it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: By doing it rightly, you end up recognizing it rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why it brings the
[SPEAKER_02]: For satipaṭṭhāna is to do complete fulfillment in regard to body, in regard to feeling, in regard to thoughts, in regard to your mind, in regard to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can do it actively, you can do it passively.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, while I'm seated right here, breathing, I'm gonna be thinking this.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or,
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm sitting here breathing, these thoughts are arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's passive.
[SPEAKER_02]: You're not actually actively thinking, but you're just recognizing what your mind does.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was, I was practicing it, that the regular, whatever arises in the mind, any kind of a, any kind of a thought, just see it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine means that for everything is appearing on their own.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, but the thing is, you have to know what not mine is, in order to be able to see particular things as they arise, as not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, first, the right view needs to be developed, in order to be applied.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, Buddha said that the noble disciple should be contemplating this is not mine, not for me, not I am, not myself, and he should
[SPEAKER_02]: That requires the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: It won't work otherwise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything's appearing on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it not enough?
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, when you're like, whatever arises and then you regard it as not mine, that's almost like a form of management for a patujana.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, you need thing to arise first.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then you can go, oh, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: But actually, you don't want thing to arise as yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't want to have to do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what freedom means.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what... arahant laid down his burden, done his work, in every conceivable regard.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is no should for him anymore, in any way.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if your practice is about doing things when this arises, that requires that thing to keep arising.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you want to start focusing on
[SPEAKER_02]: Your practice is taking you to a place whereby arising things won't require you to do anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, when they will not arise as yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the only reason you can... well, the only reason you have to be saying to whatever arises, this is not mine, is because you... first you took it as yours, and then you say it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you want to stop taking it as yours, and then you have to... you can stop taking... you can stop saying it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because now, truly, it's not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, that's the difference between this general peripheral situation you're in, while you're looking at these particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you take things as yours on this general level.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's what a... well, that's what a sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, trying to address the particular things that arise at you, as not me, not mine,
[SPEAKER_02]: Actually, if you don't see the connection between the particular determining the general and general defining the particular in return, your application of not mine, not me, won't work.
[SPEAKER_02]: It just doesn't apply to anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you see that if I regard these particular things as not belonging to me, while I see those particular things determining this sense of me, well, that's a different story.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that can only be done if you're fully aware of the situation as it has arisen, if the mindfulness is developed to a sufficient extent, to be aware of the situation while the particular things are coming and going.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it can work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes that the mindfulness of body or whatever
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes it gets lost.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes... it happens even for Arya.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is just because of Buddha generally.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, look... For Arya, less and less, and... for an Arahant, forgetting things, like forgetting particular things,
[SPEAKER_02]: does not induce ignorance anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, when you forget something, then you remember it.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was no ignorance induced in you forgetting.
[SPEAKER_02]: No sense of self induced, no appropriation induced, no upādāna induced.
[SPEAKER_02]: For Putujana, that's not the case.
[SPEAKER_02]: When Putujana forgets, his habits
[SPEAKER_02]: When he's in the state of forgetfulness, our habits of contusion, our habits that maintain avidya and everything else.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's why, like, you cannot possibly be a hundred percent mindful all the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But what you want to do is to try and be mindful as much as you can, and while you're mindful, understand the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, when you forget, like, when...
[SPEAKER_02]: When Arahant's bodhisattvas, when they were... Well, when, like, Uvayda Rādhā was still a sotāpanna, and when Sariputta died, he was very shaken, he was very affected by it.
[SPEAKER_02]: He said, everything went black, and the clouds were dark, and I couldn't... Twenty years I've been serving the Lord and listening to dhamma, and I couldn't remember a single thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that doesn't mean that he stopped being a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_02]: It means when, whatever the pressing circumstances were gone,
[SPEAKER_02]: Things were back to normal often earlier.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes I feel, when really such mindfulness is lost, I actually wonder, what does this sense of self mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes you can forget the body means what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because body means, basically, I must... Yeah, well, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sense of self is, when you are reflecting, when you're thinking, whether mindfully or not, there is an implication of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_02]: For an arahant, when he's not... when he might be forgetful in regard to things, that doesn't imply sense of self at all anymore.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because self and the whole appropriation thing is not in the things.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's in your relationship with the things, which means there is always a degree of awareness in that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, forgetfulness is in regard to particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But forgetfulness as an experience is something you can be mindful of.
[SPEAKER_02]: I... it's present and it's something you... you don't have to forget.
[SPEAKER_02]: And on that level is the level where the sense of self arises.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's why, like, even when the act of forgetting does not induce ignorance of sense of self anymore,
[SPEAKER_02]: That's when, you know, the mindfulness is being developed, when you can afford to forget particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, obviously, you forget less and less of, like, the nature of things and, generally, your memory works better if the mindfulness is developed, because that's how memory works.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, as I said, if you remember, if you're remembering that you're here in this cave, if you don't forget that, whatever you're doing, on account of you being in the cave,
[SPEAKER_02]: You can be mindful in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you forget that you're in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the thing is, you're still in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you can remember that you're in the cave and you establish your mindfulness of your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I don't mean that now you just have to keep thinking, I'm in the cave, I'm in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point of mindfulness is to recognize this relationship between peripheral and actual, between general and particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you're mindful in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, through that mindfulness, while you're in the cave, do things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Talk, sit, walk, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, you will be doing, inevitably, something.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even if it's nothing, I'm just sitting.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, that's something you're doing while you're in the cave.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's like... that's how they... how the memory works.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you read the suttas, that's why they always... when they're like...
[SPEAKER_02]: On one occasion, the Lord was staying in this province.
[SPEAKER_02]: While He was staying on that occasion in this province, He visited this forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: While he was staying in that province, visited this forest, he was sitting under the root of tree.
[SPEAKER_02]: While he was in the province, in that forest, at the root of the tree, these people came to visit.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's situation within situation within situation within situation within situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's infinite.
[SPEAKER_02]: There's none to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can go as particular as you can observe and as general as you can hold.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is not to kind of find the beginning with the end of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: The point is to fully understand the relationship between more general and then more particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's how mindfulness is established.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you don't have to necessarily start, oh, I'm in this province, in this forest, under this tree.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can just start with the body posture.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because it will be implied.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or you can just say, while I'm under this tree, at the root of the tree, these people came to visit.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm still seated at the root of this tree, we were talking about this.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm seated at the root of the tree, and we were talking about this, they asked me this particular question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that question, I gave this particular answer.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you end up remembering the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_02]: As opposed to linearly trying to list and just hold everything in mind at the same time.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't work like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how sometimes there's a... like the establishments of mind in the suttas, when they... they would have said, the monk goes off and lives in the forest, and then he observes.
[SPEAKER_02]: While in this forest, any perceptions, feelings, disturbances, based on the perceptions of the village, cannot arise.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because I'm in the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: So then, he sets his mind like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Establishes it upon the perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in the morning, when he goes Pindapa to the village, he might see unsuitable sights, hear unsuitable things, things that will provoke lust, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_02]: But because his mind is established upon perception of the forest, none of these things can
[SPEAKER_02]: And then he reflects further.
[SPEAKER_02]: He says, Because I'm established upon the more refined perception of the forest, perceptions of the village cannot disturb me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Any disturbance that arises will be on account of perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because that's where the mind is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then he can go even further.
[SPEAKER_02]: He can establish his mind upon the perception of the earth, as general as it is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Element of earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: And now, not even perceptions of the particular forest can bother him anymore, let alone the village.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's like the contemplation of the four elements.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's how it works.
[SPEAKER_02]: More general, more than...
[SPEAKER_02]: The most general is earth, water, fire and air.
[SPEAKER_02]: It doesn't get more general than that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yet, as subtle as it is, the mind can get established.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha said, be like earth, or be like fire.
[SPEAKER_02]: When you contemplate the nature of the earth, you get established through that mindfulness of... of earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't even say element of earth, because for lots of people it implies a view element.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, just say earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: Designation earth stands for solidity, stands for heart, stands for earth.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very interesting.
[SPEAKER_02]: You establish the mind... And that's the meditation on casinos, the ten casinos.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Now, nothing to do with what people do.
[SPEAKER_02]: Stare at colored discs and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just for serious misunderstanding.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, the ultimate casino, the ultimate establishment, is the establishment upon the casino of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, in the same sense that you were established upon the perceptions of the forest and established upon earth and so on, you can get established upon consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: Why?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you establish upon the nature of presence in regard to that which is present, then whatever is present cannot disturb you.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're established in regard to the nature of presence of that which is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it cannot disturb you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, literally, whatever you experience is what is present, which means whatever you experience cannot disturb you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha said that's the ultimate, that's the supreme, the most refined casino you can get established.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you don't need to go that far.
[SPEAKER_02]: Even the first element of earth is enough to abandon everything inferior to it, as the Buddha was referred to, which is evident.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because, again, whatever arises in your experience, has a degree, has an element of solidity in it, has an element of worth present, a phenomenon of worth present.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you establish upon that, you surmount everything that has that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And everything has that, which means you surmount everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: In my case, in my meditation, the practice of what I'm doing,
[SPEAKER_00]: Those things are actually a bit different things.
[SPEAKER_02]: In my case... Well, in your case, when you have thoughts coming up, or bubbles, as you refer to it, whatever, it's different perceptions, try not to forget about the general situation you're in.
[SPEAKER_02]: The fact that you're sitting in your room, on the floor, or on the chair, that's already the situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Seated in such and such situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's a general thought.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's one experience.
[SPEAKER_02]: Within that, and while you are in that position and that thought, whatever you're thinking of, whatever you're feeling, whatever you're hearing, whatever you're seeing, you can be mindful of that from that perspective.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you forget about the general situation, then you'll end up chasing every particular thought or perception at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's the problem, that there is no mindfulness there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, very little mindfulness, not established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm not thinking that the need to see all the bubbles is not mine, and that these bubbles are calling it as I am, and self-view, and the dependent relation I have to keep.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, well, see, the problem with that is, I am seeing all of this, which means your general sense of I remains unaffected.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to reverse that.
[SPEAKER_02]: You have to start indirectly whereby you see yourself first in this situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: While you're in that situation, whatever is in front of you, you start being mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: When that mindfulness is established enough, it becomes apparent then.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, you don't see it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You don't invent it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You just discern it as already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what is already there is that
[SPEAKER_02]: As I said before, the general situation you're in defines these particular bubbles and thoughts and perceptions.
[SPEAKER_02]: But they're the ones enabling the general situation to be such in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you recognize that the relationship or the dependence between this general and particular level are there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not me and I am doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not in front of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not for me.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because you're there, sitting in the room.
[SPEAKER_02]: While you're there, sitting in the room, you're thinking certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: While you're there, sitting in the room, on your chair, looking through the window, you're thinking certain things.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would you be thinking those things, if you're not in that room, sitting on that chair, looking through the window?
[SPEAKER_02]: You might well not be thinking that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, your general situation determines, defines these certain things, defines significance of those things, thought, in that situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then again, if you were not thinking in your room, on your chair, like if there was no chair, there's no room, no window, you're not thinking, would you be able to have a situation of me sitting on the chair, looking through the window, thinking these things?
[SPEAKER_02]: You couldn't.
[SPEAKER_02]: So that's how they depend on each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: And none of it can be yours for that very reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mindfulness of body means not only the body, the situation... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mindfulness of the body means mindfulness of the situation the body is in.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not the actual physical posture and observing of like, oh, this is how my knee feels in this pose or something.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's, that's all already, because you're in that situation, you can look at those particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And you can, if you want.
[SPEAKER_02]: While you're seated on the floor in a certain posture,
[SPEAKER_02]: If you start looking particular aspects of your body, your hands, your knees, your feet, your head, again, you can do it rightly, you can do it wrongly.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you do it rightly, you'll see those particular components being defined by the fact that the body is generally already there, but at the same time, without those particular components, that body couldn't have not arisen as such in the first place.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the same principle.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you just go at the components, forget about the whole picture, and just say, oh, this is not mine, this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing's changed, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: People say...
[SPEAKER_00]: If I was thinking this body, that fear, fear, fear, fear this body, and what is this body doing?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that important thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just I only have to keep seeing the feelings arise as a thought, as a bubble in the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just need to keep knowing that everything's arising, appearing on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, situation whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you have feelings arising wherever I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Again, you can, you can do that.
[SPEAKER_02]: But even then, you need a reference point in regard to what you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you might not want to be mindful of the body, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you want to be mindful of the feelings, you need a reference point in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, there is always a situation that you have to be mindful of.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is always more general and more particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's needed for mindfulness to be established.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't just be staring at the particular and being mindful, I am mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or rather, that mindfulness is not really established mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're mindful of your feelings arising, again, you can be anchored, established in your situation, in terms of bodily posture.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm walking, fear arose.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm walking, fear is present.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm walking, walking, fear is ceasing.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm walking, ah, fear is gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: As opposed to, I'm afraid.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I'm not afraid.
[SPEAKER_02]: Or, it's slightly more subtle, you can get established in terms of mind object, thought, dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's another satipaṭṭhāna, whereby I'm feeling this on account of this memory, or on account of
[SPEAKER_02]: What somebody said, or kind of something I've seen.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as that reason...
[SPEAKER_02]: I've seen something unpleasant, I feel bad.
[SPEAKER_02]: For as long as this unpleasant thing is present, bad feeling endures.
[SPEAKER_02]: Unpleasant feeling... unpleasant thing ceases, bad feeling is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in my case, suppose if I...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you see the feeling coming from that thing, not from you, belonging to that thing, not to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: And again, you can see the fear belonging to the body in the situation, not to me, I am afraid.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because of situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's how you abandon both, situation and the particular thing that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because of me.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if it's... if it comes from me, me will never be abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's important to see that relation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it not enough, suppose, if I totally forget about the situation when this body is in?
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't forget about.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can ignore it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the meditation, suppose, if I just keep seeing the bubbles arising in that angled circle.
[SPEAKER_02]: The only reason particular things can arise is from the perspective of a more general situation that it's already there.
[SPEAKER_02]: In other words, the movement of arising and ceasing is impossible if there is no static point in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's just the nature of things.
[SPEAKER_02]: If everything is moving, there's no movement.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the fact that you discern bubbles coming and going, means there is a point that is still in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that point is your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is more general than those particular changing bubbles.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you cannot but not have it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can only ignore it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's not good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean that you can't go to
[SPEAKER_01]: The Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole thing...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not... Like, the Eightfold Path are the eight components that need to be developed.
[SPEAKER_02]: But it's not one, and then you develop two, and then you develop...
[SPEAKER_02]: In Samādhiti Sutta, the sutta that talks about it, the main sutta, Madhyamika Nine, he says that
[SPEAKER_02]: Every of those factors is governed by the first factor of the right view.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, knowing things rightly is the first precondition.
[SPEAKER_02]: Knowing things rightly would make your meditation right, would make your reading the suttas right, would make your actions right, your sīla right, everything will become right if you know that it's right.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how it's done.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the thing is, people misunderstand meditation as a separate thing from contemplating the dhamma, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_02]: One, like, meditation brings contemplation, contemplation brings meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if your meditation is not making any difference to your contemplation, it means that's a wrong meditation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And he said it's like two yolks pulling each other.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if one goes forward, what the other one will have, because they're connected.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if you're putting forward samatha, vipassana will be there.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like, oh, I'll do samatha here, then I'll go the other way and do a bit of vipassana there.
[SPEAKER_02]: No.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're doing vipassana, your meditation is coming with it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can't even conceive being separate.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if you read the suttas of meditation, like ānāpānasati, it's all this practice of this mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_02]: In regard to more general, like, while I'm breathing, I will feel this.
[SPEAKER_02]: While I'm breathing, I'll think that.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, being skilled in recognizing situation, you're inevitably... you can't even conceive not being in situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if you think I'm not in a situation, that is your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you don't even have to constantly think about your situation, but in your daily life, the fact that there are particular things like, oh, I need to sweep this floor now and clean this up.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's only possible because the floor and the cave and all the significance of the whole thing is already present in my situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then I can attend to these particular things.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't forget the situation?
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, you can forget it, but you can't escape it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You forget it when you're not mindful.
[SPEAKER_02]: You ignore it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, you get caught up in particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And then, you suffer more on account of particular things, or you get elated more on account of particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: In either way, you get moved much more by the particular things.
[SPEAKER_02]: You suffer.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's probably, I don't know, very new for you.
[SPEAKER_02]: To hear this.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, but even if it's not, it's not something... it's not something you can just hear somebody say once, and then you... oh, you can get the idea.
[SPEAKER_02]: But you have to keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, like, the nature of intention works the same.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, because you had intention to come here today to see me and talk about the dhamma, that's a very general intention you had.
[SPEAKER_02]: While that intention was still present,
[SPEAKER_02]: You went and hired a tuk-tuk.
[SPEAKER_02]: There was a more particular intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Calling the driver, telling him to come, giving him the time.
[SPEAKER_02]: Walking to the tuk-tuk, sitting in the tuk-tuk, being in the tuk-tuk, coming here, walking, finding the place, getting lost, realizing that you were lost, finding the right way.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of those particular intentions were within the intention of you wanting to be here, toṭa dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: If that general intention, you wanting to be here, toṭa dhamma, disappears,
[SPEAKER_02]: But, if you suddenly change your mind on the way here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Oh, I can't go there today.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_02]: You go back.
[SPEAKER_02]: All of those particular intentions, then, lose their general, like a, significant direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: You change your mind.
[SPEAKER_02]: Suddenly I called and said I had to go to hospital or something like that.
[SPEAKER_02]: If the general intention of you wanting to be here
[SPEAKER_02]: Changes, whether through you or through the circumstances, all of the particular intention, then, oh, I cannot go to there, therefore, why would you be calling a tuk-tuk, telling him to bring you here?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's gone.
[SPEAKER_02]: If you're about to make a phone call to call a driver, but then you found out that you can't come, you're not going to be doing this particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that's how you can be mindful of all of those particular intentions, by knowing what the general intention is in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, obviously, there is no end to generality, nor there is an end to particularity.
[SPEAKER_02]: But that's not important.
[SPEAKER_02]: You won't have to reach the end or the first point, because there won't be any.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole point is to understand that relationship.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, if sometimes you... like, you had an intention to come here, but then your mindfulness is not established upon that intention, well, then you can establish your mindfulness upon even more general intention of... intention of you wanting to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a result of you wanting to understand the dhamma, you want to come here particularly and talk about the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a result of you wanting to understand the dhamma, you want to come here and talk the dhamma, you want to call the tuk-tuk driver and tell him to come at certain time and bring you here.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a result of all of that, you will sit in a tuk-tuk for two and a half hours.
[SPEAKER_02]: As a result of all of that, you will be... and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_02]: So you can pick any of those things, as long as you're mindful in regard to the particular.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not just chase the particular or get lost in the general.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the relationship that's important.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that relationship is sankhāra-sankhāta-dhamma.
[SPEAKER_02]: The whole experience is dual in that sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: Everything, every experience falls into that.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the... That's when you're calling it fundamental structure.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the structure of the experience, the structure of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the Buddha said, even if somebody is remembering one previous life, five previous lives, five hundred previous lives, all they're remembering is these five or one among them.
[SPEAKER_02]: These five aggregates or one among them.
[SPEAKER_02]: Nothing, nothing out of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within
[SPEAKER_02]: It's all within the same structure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intention and this choosing, these things are actually really confusing, because, like, the sense of self is really, like, intended.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's the most, it's the closest, closest relation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, intention is there, where the sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_02]: But again, if you start looking in terms of the situation, the only reason you can intend to drink that glass of water is because it's already there in your situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the particular intention... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You can choose what's already given.
[SPEAKER_02]: If it hasn't been given and displayed through your senses, you can't even conceive it, let alone intend it.
[SPEAKER_02]: But if you're just looking and focusing on the particular, then your intention will always feel very direct, always feel me and I am.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, yeah, I want to drink water.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the only reason I can drink water is because there is water here.
[SPEAKER_02]: Drinkable water, and there's a little... And then you realize, even this whole sense of, I want to do this, is actually determined by that general situation.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because if that thing changes, no matter how strong my sense of self is, if there is no water to drink it here, that intention will not make sense.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I might have to go somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's totally up to you.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, I think it is... Well, if you start looking through a situation, the relationship becomes more and more apparent.
[SPEAKER_02]: The relationship that is mutually determining and kind of not requiring your sense of self at all.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the more you are aware of it, the more you discern it, the less of it is yours.
[SPEAKER_02]: Externally, not much can change, not much needs to change.
[SPEAKER_02]: Obviously, virtues, behavior and so on, but that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it is actually quite important that it all arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: What kind of...